Sue Darby

Technical Writer Webmistress at iA3, open to new opportunities

sue.a.darby@gmail.com

Summary

I am a specialist at bridging the gap between business managers and IT professionals, among the rare group of people who can translate business needs to the IT staff and the mid to high levels of technical information to the business users. I excel at identifying execution steps, building processes and diagrams with detailed instructions for use. I am passionate about helping people do tasks more efficiently and am always looking for a better way to solve problems. My experience as a Senior Services Technician combined with my double B.S. Degree in Business Management & Technology: Concentration in Business Applications and B.S. Degree in Business Management & Technology (with Honors) has given me the foundation necessary for success. I am looking for programming work using the variety of languages I know and learn a few more on the way. I want to make an impact on a project. I have a variety of other skills to offer as well. I am looking for opportunities in the Mat-Su Valley of Alaska or Anchorage or virtually working with businesses for programming, technical writing, business analysis and web development. Get to know me via www.sue-a-darby.com and my network of websites I have been working on for 15+ years. I have a variety of topics and samples spread across 8 sites. Please be specific as to what I can do for you as a contact or what you might have to offer me for career leads.

Experience

Technical Writer & Webmistress at iA3

October 2015 - Present (5 months)

iA3 is a service that gives you access to information and analytics about any automated systems you may have; anywhere, anytime. I am currently involved with the website, social media, Wikipedia and marketing efforts while learning and growing into a role as a technical writer.

Senior Services Technician at State of Alaska, Division of Senior & Disabilities, Provider Certification & Compliance

February 2014 - Present (2 years 1 month)

*Effectively explain ideas and information to both technical and non-technical users *Convert New Provider Certification Application to fill in PDF for public use *Design and implementation of the and Habilitation Homes Project to connect licensed homes with recipients and certified agencies; original and Critical Incident Report *Tracking system and statistics generation *Design improved filing and labeling system, archive process, electronic file system, document naming structure, letter template editing and standardization *Design charts and graphs for Unit, Department, State and Federal reports; UML diagrams, translate into written processes; gather information, develop content including graphics, proofread and edit technical documents *Develop process for archival and offsite storage of files including training

materials and procedure development *Develop plan to create database connections for previously invisible information working with management and IT *Ability to understand, analyze, apply, & explain complex program statutes, regulations, policies, & procedures *Communicates effectively with both technical & non-technical users *Adjust workflow to complete critical tasks in a timely manner *Develop specific process for processing archival & offsite storage of files *Policy & procedure development *Maintain records of files & version controls *Write technically detailed, illustrated instructions for processes

Virtual Office Support Administrator at Alaska Office Specialists

October 2008 - Present (7 years 5 months)

Alaska Office Specialists is a service-based business offering the services of technical writing, business writing, grant writing, document template creation, report writing, content writing (minimum standards apply to all writing). Hosting, setup and maintenance of WordPress based sites, social media management. visit www.alaskaos.com for more information. on hiatus

Owner, Designer, Web Master at Sue's Tiny Costumes

September 1995 - Present (20 years 6 months)

- Manage small business including product development, class development, web design & maintenance, marketing & budget Write technically detailed, illustrated instructions for processes & doll patterns
- Distance Education Teacher for pattern drafting classes Research & write business, marketing, & merchandising plans Project management including task management, goals, timelines and GANTT Charts
- Set project goals, determine risks, prepare contingency plan, & time line for achievement Collect & analyze data on customers to identify potential markets Web site design & maintenance of hand coded websites Install & maintain Wordpress sites Proficient in white hat SEO techniques Track keywords, visitors & other analytical data for each site Troubleshoot hosting issues on hiatus

Office Assistant II at State of Alaska, Division of Senior & Disabilities, Provider Certification & Compliance

May 2008 - February 2014 (5 years 10 months)

Transitioned to the Senior Services Technician as my work as an Office Assistant II became more complex than the Office Assistant II position allows. • Ability to understand, analyze, apply, & explain complex program statutes, regulations, policies, & procedures • Communicates effectively with both technical & non-technical users • Adjust workflow to complete critical tasks in a timely manner • Develop specific process for processing archival & offsite storage of files • Policy & procedure development • Maintain records of files & version controls • Write technically detailed, illustrated instructions for processes • Master Certified Office 2003, SharePoint (site owner) • Visio, Star UML, Project, • Organizing training sessions; materials gathering, staff/location coordination, equipment setup • Train additional staff on various processes & assign tasks overseeing accuracy

Career Development Mentor & Computer Instructor at Nine Star Education & Employment Services

April 2006 - April 2008 (2 years 1 month)

• Organized training sessions; materials gathering, staff/location coordination, equipment setup • Developed class curriculum • Taught computer classes to adults • Taught goal setting workshops • Developed basic computer classes or work one on one with students to develop skills • Answered student questions about various software applications • Aided students in preparation for the Microsoft Office Specialist exams • Assessed clients for barriers & brainstorm ways to overcome them • Drafted & edited resumes, cover letters & other business correspondence • Conferred with clients to determine what program will be most helpful • Conducted job-matching to find good fit between clients & hiring companies • Directed clients to appropriate resources & assists clients in their use of outside assistance

Skills & Expertise

Technical Writing

Business Analysis

Data Analysis

Documentation

Business Process Design

Problem Solving

Project Planning

Software Documentation

Writing

Analysis

HTML

Microsoft Office

CSS

Process Improvement

Training

Project Management

Strategic Planning

SharePoint

Web Development

Web Design

Databases

WordPress

Quality Assurance

Content Management

Management

Editing

Research

Time Management

Teaching

Team Leadership

Dreamweaver

Troubleshooting

Team Building

Event Management Social Media Marketing Human Resources SEO Marketing

Interests

About Sue: http://www.sue-a-darby.com/about.html Technical Writing, Web Master, Marketing, Business Owner, Photography, HTML, CSS, JavaScript, Perl, VisualBasic, Product Design & Development, Document Design, & Formatting, Streamline Administrative Processes, Database Improvements, Data Tracking, Report Processes, Project Management, Task Management, Goals, Budgets, Timelines, GANTT Charts, Master Certified MS Office 2003, MS Office 95-2010, MS Project, MS Visio, MS SharePoint 2007-2010, OneNote, AdobePro X & XI, Adobe DC, Corel Draw Suite, UML. Visio,

Projects

Professional Curriculum Vitae

January 1994 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

Website which showcases skills in web development, marketing, technical writing, programming languages, software, project planning and management as well as further details about work history.

Portfolio of Work Samples

October 2006 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

A selection of work samples. The site includes examples of UMLs, Forms, Tutorials, and Business Process snippets. http://work-samples.sue-a-darby.com/

Habilitation Homes Project

May 2010 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

Provider Certification has a number of different providers and even sub-contracted providers of services for those with disabilities. The sub-contractors while important were not found in the internal database and thus no one knew where the clients were being served. As a brainstorm about this issue I asked management and then IT why we could not connect these contracted homes to the provider oversight agency within the database in a similar fashion to another provider type. The ongoing project to add contracted providers to the current DS3 database system was born. It is enabling the Provider Certification & Compliance Reviewers to conduct on site visits to ensure health and welfare of clients in habilitation settings thus maintaining compliance with Federal regulations and statutes under the Home & Community Based Waiver Program. In addition to the initial entry and connections for each contracted home, maintenance for each record is conducted as the host agency is recertified. Additionally, reports have been created to track and more easily see which homes contract with each agency or agencies. This ensures there is less fraud and Medicaid abuse.

Alaska Office Specialists

October 2009 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

Virtual Assistant Services such as Writing Blog writing Article Writing Content Writing (Minimum article length 300-500 words) Editing Business writing Creative writing Microsoft Office Letters Memos Design documents Mail merge, mailing services Reports Newsletters and management Excel data entry Access Databases Power Point Presentations Process Diagramming UML Diagramming Business Process Consulting and design Organization charts Social Media and Email Services Email Management Multiple Inboxes E-mail responses to customer inquiries Escalate only as needed Email management, sorting mail, tags Email marketing campaigns with MailChimp Website Management WordPress Website Content Management Install Wordpress Install InfiniteWP for multiple sites Configurations and setup of themes and plugins FaceBook, Twitter, Pinterest etc Technology Coaching Want to learn MS Office yourself or how to manage your WordPress site? Contact us for a coaching session. Rates vary based on topics. Any service listed can be coached.

Electronic Folder Organization

March 2014 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

Develop a standardized electronic folder system to organize notices, scanned applications and other documentation required for provider certification and compliance. Setup folders, migrate information with IT assistance to new folder system and ensure remainder of unit complies with new standards training and providing assistance and guidance as needed.

Archives

May 2008 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

As the division subject matter expert I have had a hand in the developent of the SharePoint Site that tracks all the files that are sent to Archives or Off Site Storage. Working closely with the techs I helped find and fix bugs in an older system for calculating retention times, update the form to match the required form for Archiving and work as an administrator of the site adding new team members to the site. Recently there has been a complete change of Administrative staff responsible for part of the process and I was asked to step in to help train them in what the division has done in the last several years. I am also part of a team that is determining the fate of the site as the division moves towards a new database system. Gather, categorize, folder, label and enter into a spreadsheet or database thousands of files dating back to 1996 and prepare for archiving. Oversee volunteer efforts for data entry and correctly calculate the disposition date before submitting for pick up. Recall files for records requests or other litigation as needed. Over 160 cubic feet of data has been sent off site for storage or archiving. Previously the Archive SharePoint site, built in SharePoint 2007 and converted to 2010 was not computing retention times correctly. I took the lead to work with the SharePoint Developers to update and improve the system. In the process working closely to test and deploy fixes and becoming a site admin for the test and production sites due to my knack for finding the problems or suggesting where the issue might be within the code.

Self Published Author

June 2001 to Present

Members:Sue Darby

I have had a love of dolls all my life as well as a love of sewing. I combined these loves with a talent for pattern making and wrote not just one book on pattern making for dolls but another for drafting in miniature as well. The two books were a handcrafted and illustrated technical writing achievement that now reside in the Library of Congress as of June of 2001. Based on the books I took them from print to digital format before it was popular to have electronic books. I also used text based chat rooms to teach classes to individuals all over the world.

Publications

Pattern Making for Dolls

Copyright June 1, 2001

Authors: Sue Darby

Step-by-step guide to drafting for small dolls and fashion dolls. Fully illustrated and explained in detail how easy it is to measure and draft patterns "by the numbers" for dolls as small as 8" tall up to 46" tall. Originally self published in hard copy and now available as an e-book.

Pattern Drafting for Miniatures

Copyright June 1, 2001

Authors: Sue Darby

Library of Congress http://lccn.loc.gov/2004540327

Pattern Consultant

International Doll Magazine June 2005

Authors: Sue Darby

Multiple articles in bi-monthly doll magazine including Little Bo Peep, Wedding Gown and "Dirty Dancing" inspired dresses for several dolls

Published Patterns

Dolls In MIniature June 1, 2004

Authors: Sue Darby

Pattern for miniature smocked baby dress for 1/12 scale doll.

Education

GNC Web Creations Online Search Engine Optimization Class

none, SEO, 2002 - 2020

Activities and Societies: Actively participate in online forum and group discussions on business and building websites.

Charter College

Bachelors/Associates, Business Management Practice & Office Applications, 2006 - 2009

Activities and Societies: Dean's List, Alpha Beta Kappa, Alpha Gamma Sigma

Charter College

Bachelors Business Management & Information Technology, 2006 - 2009

Solano Community College

Certificate, Fashion Design, 1995 - 1997

Activities and Societies: n/a

Fairfield High

Diploma, 1992 - 1994

Activities and Societies: Scarlet Brigade Marching Band Future Farmers of America

Honors and Awards

Alpha Beta Kappa Honors Society, Charter College, Anchorage, AK

May 2009

Life Honors Society for 3.85 GPA

Dean's List, Charter College, Anchorage, AK

Every semester for high GPA

Microsoft Office 2003 Master, Nine Star Education & Employment Services, Anchorage, AK

Microsoft

April 2009

Completed 6 tests for Microsoft office which high passing scores. 2 years of Americorps service as a computer instructor but did not seek Master Instructor despite being eligible for it.

Courses

Bachelors/Associates, Business Management Practice & Office Applications

Charter College

Technical Writing

Project Management

Statistics

Research Methodolgies

Advanced Web Development

Visual Basic.NET

Operations Management

Marketing

Office Assistant II

State of Alaska, Division of Senior & Disabilities,

Provider Certification & Compliance

Archiving Basics State of Alaska

Introduction to Share Point with Lab State of Alaska

Introduction to Supervisor Training State of Alaska

Basic Care Coordination Training for QA State of

Alaska

Introduction to Office 2007 State of Alaska

Senior Services Technician

State of Alaska, Division of Senior & Disabilities,

Provider Certification & Compliance

COGNOS

HIPAA Security 2008-2014 State of Alaska

.....

Independent Coursework

HTML 5

CSS

JavaScript

PHP

MYSQL

Web design

Certifications

Microsoft Office Master

Microsoft March 2009

MSOS: Microsoft Word 2003

Microsoft March 2007

MSOS: Microsoft Excel 2003
Microsoft September 2007
MSOS: Microsoft Access 2003
Microsoft November 2007

MSOS: Microsoft PowerPoint 2003

Microsoft October 2007

MSOE: Microsoft Word 2003 Expert

Microsoft November 2007

MSOE: Microsoft Excel 2003 Expert

Microsoft March 2009

Languages

French

(Elementary proficiency)

Volunteer Experience

Volunteer at AmeriCorps

April 2006 - April 2008 (2 years 1 month)

Sue Darby

Technical Writer Webmistress at iA3, open to new opportunities

sue.a.darby@gmail.com



4 person has recommended Sue

"I studied with Sue in an online class for SEO. Sue is an inspiration to me and other classmates. Working a website up to number one in the search engines is no small feat and our whole class seemed to click. That was years ago, and we are mostly all still keeping in touch. A bond of sorts was formed with that original class and I am proud to be a part of it."

— Carla Schwille, studied with Sue at GNC Web Creations Online Search Engine Optimization Class

"Sue was one of my students at Charter College. She was on time and completed all of her work in a professional manner. Sue was also helpful to her fellow students."

— **Sandra Charlton-Anchorage**, taught Sue at Charter College

"Sue was a bright and engaged student, who was always willing to participate and brought great insight to whatever class she was in. I had her as a student in multiple classes, and always enjoyed her presence. Her work was of the highest caliber, and her writing was always clear and well thought out. She worked well in group situations, as well as on her own. Sue would be an acceptional addition to any workplace."

— **Dr. Hillary Hodges**, taught Sue at Charter College

"I was Sue;s instructor in various courses at Charter College and I have become familiar with her work through discussions with her and in analyzing her written assignments and tests. Her understanding of the course material and her ability to communicate is excellent. I am sure she is going to have an excellent career. In my view, she epitomizes the student who has high aims, intellectual ability, and the drive to succeed."

— William Jamison, taught Sue at Charter College

Contact Sue on LinkedIn